A Guide to the Taconic Foundation records FA407
Rockefeller Archive Center
Taconic Foundation records
1958-2013
Rockefeller Archive Center
Taconic Foundation
Currier, Stephen R.
FA407
94 Cubic Feet 206 document boxes, 2 standard records boxes, 3 oversized flat boxes, and 2 card files
2.14 Gigabytes 839 digital files
Arrangement
The Taconic Foundation records are arranged into four series: Series 1 - Grants; Series 2 - Board Materials; Series 3 - Organization Records; Series 4 - Tax Records.
Biographical / Historical
Philanthropists Stephen R. Currier and his wife Audrey Bruce Currier established the Taconic Foundation in 1958.
Stephen Richard Currier, born in Santa Fe, New Mexico, in 1930, was the son of Richard and Mary Prue Currier. His father, who was descended from the family of the lithographer Nathaniel Currier, was a painter. Currier's parents divorced in 1936. His mother, an editor for Vogue magazine, married the prominent arts patron Edward M. M. Warburg in 1939. Stephen Currier was educated at St. Bernard's School and Horace Mann–Lincoln School in New York and the George School in Bucks County, Pennsylvania. He enrolled at Harvard in 1948.
Audrey Bruce Currier, born in 1933 to the diplomat David Bruce and his wife Ailsa Mellon Bruce, was the first grandchild of Andrew W. Mellon. The Bruces separated in the early 1940s and divorced in 1945. Audrey attended the Brearley School and the Foxcroft School, and enrolled at Radcliffe in 1952, from which she graduated in 1956.
Audrey and Stephen met while students at Harvard and Radcliffe and married in November 1955. After Audrey's graduation, they settled in New York. They had three children: Andrea Bruce Currier, Lavinia McClendon Currier, and Michael Stephen Currier.
Audrey and Stephen both hailed from wealthy families, and they received a steady flow of income from the Mellon family trust. Private and personally reticent (Audrey, in particular, was extremely shy), they created the Taconic Foundation in 1958 with a goal of channeling their giving toward areas neglected by other foundations and where they could have the greatest impact. Creating equality of opportunity — in education, housing, employment, and civil rights — became the new foundation's enduring mission. The foundation initially limited its grantmaking to the New York City area and New England, where it focused particularly on issues of child welfare and mental illness. The focus soon evolved into a broader concern with race relations, legal reform, and civil rights. Stephen Currier became a crucial mediator between the Federal government and civil rights leaders. The Taconic Foundation was instrumental in bringing civil rights organizations together in support of the Voter Education Project, and through the foundation Steven Currier launched the Potomac Institute and Urban America to bring attention and research to bear on problems of racial justice, equal opportunity, and the urban crisis.
In January 1967, Audrey and Stephen Currier perished when their plane disappeared in the Caribbean. John G. Simon, president of the Taconic Foundation, and his wife Claire, good friends of the Curriers, took guardianship of the Currier children.
The Taconic Foundation continued on course for some forty-five years after the Curriers' disappearance, closing up in 2013. Equality of opportunity remained its central priority, even as its program areas evolved to focus on issues of housing rights and affordable housing, community and economic development, and youth employment.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Taconic Foundation donated its records to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated May 31, 2012.
Separated Materials
Special Formats (digital media, library materials, oversize, and photographic material) have been separated from the body of the collection. All pertinent items are assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
Scope and Contents
The Taconic Foundation was in its own words, "a fairly small foundation trying to address some very big problems." Founded in 1958 by philanthropists Stephen and Audrey Currier, the Taconic Foundation worked consistently during its fifty-five-year existence to combat social inequities and promote equality of opportunity. Under Stephen Currier's lead, Taconic was at the forefront in organizing support for the civil rights movement and seeking solutions to the urban crisis. Initial program areas focused on race relations, mental health, and child development. Later programs evolved to focus on families and youth, educational innovation, community organizing, housing and neighborhood development, and youth employment.
Along with supporting research into particular issues, the Foundation led by funding demonstration projects or "model" programs, such as its youth employment programs. When necessary — as in its fight against red-lining or exclusionary zoning practices — the Taconic Foundation did not shy away from funding legal remedies, supporting litigation and monitoring to ensure compliance with the law. Taconic also helped pioneer the concept of "program-related investments" as a source of capital for minority or low-income neighborhoods. From its early days, the Taconic Foundation targeted problems, devised solutions, and engaged others, including the government, to follow suit.
The Taconic Foundation enjoyed remarkable continuity in its membership and governance from its founding to its final closure in 2013, and many trustees served for life. When incorporated in May 1958, the Taconic Foundation board consisted of Stephen R. Currier, chair; Audrey Bruce Currier, and Lloyd K. Garrison. Jane Lee Eddy joined the same year as executive secretary, retiring (as executive director) only in 1997, when the foundation transferred responsibility for its administration to J.P. Morgan (she continued to serve as trustee). Child psychologist Edith Entenman and attorney and professor John G. Simon joined the board in 1959. After the Curriers' death in 1967, John Simon presided over the foundation for the remainder of its existence. In 1960, the board elected Dorothy Hirshon as a trustee, and in 1961 added Harold C. Fleming, executive director of the Potomac Institute. Other trustees included: Vernon Jordan (served 1976–1992), Alan J. Dworsky (1980– 2013), Michael Currier (1984–1987), Susan Curnan (1987–circa 1994), Melvin Mister (1989–circa 2012), L. F. Boker Doyle (1989–2013), Bill Green (1993–2002), Hildy Simmons (2000–2013), Oliver W. Wesson (2000–2013), and Veronica White (2004–2010).
As the Taconic Foundation marked its fiftieth anniversary in 2008, the board considered its history and planned its legacy. It commissioned historical timelines, program reviews, and oral history interviews to document the foundation's accomplishments. The process of Quo Vadimus (Where are we going?) reflection, first begun in the mid-1990s but ever present as the board acknowledged its limited resources and the impending retirement of its long-term officers, turned to a wide-ranging consideration of how to close a foundation. The resulting spend-down endowed a program of Taconic Fellows at three of the foundation's long-term grantee organizations, made final grants to other significant grantees, and awarded several smaller grants to organizations chosen by each of the trustees.
In a coda to its spend-down, at its final meeting of March 28, 2013, the Taconic Foundation board transferred leadership to the grandchildren of Stephen and Audrey Currier, who assumed the mantle of a reborn and newly named Taconic Foundation for Social Justice.
The Taconic Foundation records document the foundation's board deliberations and grantmaking from its founding in 1958 to its closure in 2013. Significant program areas include race relations, voting rights, urban renewal, housing rights, neighborhood preservation and economic development, school reform, mental health, child welfare, and youth employment. Organizations funded, and in some cases established, by the Taconic Foundation include the Cooperative Assistance Fund, the Voter Education Project, the Southern Regional Council, the Potomac Institute, the Suburban Action Institute, and Urban America. While the foundation's projects particularly targeted problems in New York City neighborhoods, it also worked on behalf of race relations in the South and of housing reform in Chicago, Philadelphia, and other metropolitan and suburban areas. The Smokey House Center, developed on the Curriers' property in Danby, Vermont, provided the Taconic Foundation with a model for its youth employment training program.
While Stephen Currier was widely credited for his civil rights leadership, there is very little documentation of his personal activism in the Taconic Foundation records, and the collection contains no record of his work with the Council on United Civil Rights Leadership. A letter from Jane Lee Eddy to Dorothy Height (March 9, 1991, in box 56, folder 579), indicates that "those records were part of the Curriers' personal files and were separated from Taconic materials after their death." The Curriers' personal papers remain in the possession of the family.
Around October 1988, the Taconic Foundation donated "seven boxes of material relating to the civil rights movement" to the New York Public Library's Schomburg Center, and some forty-nine books to the Municipal Reference and Research Center of the City of New York. Presumably, the Schomburg donation also consisted of books, but we have not been able to confirm this fact.
The Taconic Foundation records are comprised of paper and digital records, integrated in one arrangement and description. Records include correspondence, memos, reports, publications, and photographs. Digital records are in standard file formats for documents, spreadsheets, and presentations (mainly .doc, .xls, .ppt, and PDFs). While there may be some duplication between the paper and digital components of hybrid files, there is no exact correspondence between the two formats, and the file contents do not necessarily coincide.
Child development; Child welfare; Civil rights movement; Community development, Urban; Discrimination in housing; Educational change; Housing rehabilitation; Southern States -- Race relations; Urban renewal -- Citizen participation; Vocational education; Youth -- Employment; New York (N.Y.)
- Grants, 1958-2010; 1; 76.73 Cubic Feet 172 document boxes (including 1 half-box), 2 oversized flat boxes; 2.02 Gigabytes 35 digital files
  Scope and Contents
  The Grants series documents the Taconic Foundation's grantmaking from its inception in the late 1950s and early 1960s up to, but generally not including, its final grant cycles and spend-down in 2008-2012. Records concerning these latter grants are found, for the most part, not in the Grants series, but in the Organization Records series, under "Grantmaking and Foundation History" or under "Spend-Down Process." These late grants are grouped collectively rather than by individual grantee.
  Grant files contain proposals, correspondence, and reports, and sometimes publications or literature relating to the institution or the particular grant. Most grant files also include one or more grant memos, which Taconic Foundation officers wrote for each new grant or renewal, setting forth for the board the terms of the request, the nature of the organization and its history with Taconic, previous funding, the pros and cons of the proposed grant, its fit with the Taconic program, and the recommended action.
  The Taconic Foundation also funded a number of "Projects" that produced research and reports on issues of concern to the foundation or that resulted in the creation of new organizations that then benefited from Taconic grant support. Projects included, for example, the Assessment Project on Negro Needs, Davidoff's and Gold's proposals for low-income housing in lower Manhattan, the Voter Education Project, the Smokey House Project, and the Cooperative Assistance Fund.
  A number of simple correspondence files are interspersed in this grants series. Each of these files generally contains just a few pieces of correspondence. While some correspondents have connections to Taconic projects, for the most part the correspondence files seem to be remnants of either a finite correspondence or a larger series. There is no general correspondence series in the Taconic records, and the Grants series constitutes the main series of files.
  The Grants series is fairly comprehensive, but it is not a complete set of grant files. Some significant reports, such as Mary Conway Kohler's study of Youth and Work in New York, are not found in the files. Records are sparse or sometimes lacking for some of the Taconic Foundation's early grants. Many of the early programs were first launched with personal grants from the Curriers before the Taconic Foundation assumed their funding, and these hybrid origins may, perhaps, account for some of the gaps.
  Arrangement
  The Grants series is arranged alphabetically by name of institution or subject.
  - Abbott House, 1963, 1968, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ACCION New York, 1994-2007 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - Advisory for Open Education, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Grant to support Creative Teaching Workshop, an in-service teacher training program, at Public School 3, in New York City. Administered by the Advisory for Open Education, Cambridge, MA. File also includes a proposal to the JDR 3rd Fund, Education through the Arts Project.
  - Advocates for Children of New York, Inc., 2002-2004, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ahmann, Mathew, 1968-1973, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Ahmann, formerly executive director of the National Catholic Conference for Interracial Justice, 1960-1968, submits proposal to form a consortium of Chicago colleges (known as the Checagou Institute) to address problems of urban poor, 1969. In 1970-1971, requests seed grant for proposed Foundation for Mexican-American Affairs.
  - Albert Einstein College of Medicine, 1988-1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Support for Teenage Mothers Grandmothers' Program
  - Albert G. Oliver Program, Inc., 1985-1997 (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - American Bar Association, Legal Services Back-Up Centers, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - American Bar Association, Legal Services Back-Up Centers, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - American Civil Liberties Union Foundation: General
    Also includes material relating to land use program and work by New York Civil Liberties Union against exclusionary zoning, 1974.
    - 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1981-1983, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - American Civil Liberties Union Foundation: Land Use Program
    Support for program of research and litigation to promote land use policies consistent with equal opportunity in housing (cases concerning beach use, exclusionary zoning, and government action on dispersed housing). File includes legal briefs and supplementary material concerning land use and exclusionary zoning.
    - 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - American Friends Service Committee, Inc.: General, 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Program in Prince Edward County, VA, 1960-1961, and housing program in Philadelphia.
  - American Friends Service Committee, Inc.: General, 1972, 1977-1988 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Includes proposals for Southern Rural Housing, Southeastern Public Education, and Neighborhood Youth Employment projects.
  - American Friends Service Committee, Inc.: Fair Housing Handbook, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - American Friends Service Committee, Inc.: School Desegregation Task Force, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - American Jewish Committee
    Support for the National Job-Linked Housing Center.
    - 1971-1974 March (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 1974 April - December (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - American Jewish Committee (Nigeria/Biafra Relief), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - American Planning and Civic Association
    Related Materials
    In 1965 the American Planning and Civic Association changed its name to Urban America, and later materials are filed under that name.
    - 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - American Reading Council, 1987, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Grant of $10,000 to support use of "Open Sesame" reading program at Public School 192, in New York City.
  - American Social Health Association
    The Taconic Foundation provided funding for a study of drug addiction in the United States.
    - 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1965-1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - American Society of Planning Officials, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Support for report on promoting housing for low- and moderate-income families.
  - A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund (APREF), 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Architectural Forum (Whitney)
    Biographical / Historical
    Whitney Publications published Architectural Forum from December 1969 until its discontinuation in March 1974. Urban America had published the magazine from 1965-1969, but sold it to Whitney Publications as of December 1, 1969.
    - General, 1969-1973, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      The file includes correspondence with Peter Blake, as editor of Architectural Forum and then of Architecture Plus.
    - Whitney-Urban America Agreement, 1969-1974 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      Contract between Urban America and Whitney Publications, Inc., November 21, 1969, for the sale of Architectural Forum to Whitney; correspondence concerning Whitney's obligations under the contract.
  - Argus Community (Elizabeth Sturz)), 1976, 1979-1987 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    In 1987 the Taconic Foundation awarded a grant of $18,000 to the Argus Community to support a supervisor and worksite training program in Argus buildings. File also includes earlier proposals for a group home for young women without effective family relationships and for a Job Horizons program.
  - Argus Community (Volunteer Opportunities Inc.)
    Support for group home development for adolescents in the South Bronx. Argus Community program originally established in 1969 by Volunteer Opportunities Inc.
    - 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Asian American Legal Defense and Education Fund, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Asian Americans for Equality, Inc.
    - 2002 January-March (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - 2002 April-September (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies, 1984, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    Proposal by Dick Clark on "U.S. - Soviet Relations: Planning for 1985 and Beyond." Copy of Annual Report, 1994.
  - Aspira Inc.
    Formerly Puerto Rican - Hispanic Leadership Forum Inc.
    - 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      Includes report and interview notes on self-help organizations in the Puerto Rican community, August 1960.
    - 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - 1964-1973 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - 1974-1988 (Box 5, Folder 48)
      Proposals for leadership development and educational support program for Hispanic youth.
  - Assessment Project on Negro Needs
    The Assessment Project, undertaken in 1963, engaged African American leaders as consultants to analyze and discuss the long-range needs of African American citizens. Participants prepared analyses of policies relating to African American education, employment, housing, health, welfare, self-image, and citizenship education.
    - General, 1963-1964, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Meeting Summaries, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Reports
      Some report files are arranged by number and others have been grouped with them by topic. We have supplied the subject labels.
      - Assessment Project (Women), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 51)
        Memoranda on "The Negro Woman" and "Women in Minority Groups," by Dorothy I. Height. File also includes memoranda by James Farmer, Whitney M. Young, Jr., and Jack Greenberg, April 11-12, 1963, on the Assessment Project's "Remaining Tasks."
      - Assessment Project (Labor), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 52)
        Study on the Negro in the Labor Force, by Mahlon T. Puryear.
      - Assessment Project (Education), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 53)
        Report by Edward Warner Brice on "Education of Negroes."
      - Assessment Project (Education), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 54)
        File contains papers on "Compensatory and Strengthening Programs: Education of Negroes, by William J. Trent, Jr.; "The Educationally and Culturally Disadvantaged," by Eddie G. Ponder, June 1963; and "Some Comments on the Education of Negroes for Occupations Other than Professional," by Francis A. Gregory.
      - Assessment Project (Education), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 55)
        Study on "Vocational Guidance and Counseling of Negro Youth," by Ann Tanneyhill.
      - Assessment Project (Public Welfare Programs), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 56)
        Study on "Public Welfare Programs and the Negro, with emphasis on the Negro Child," by Inabel B. Lindsay.
      - Assessment Project (Private Social Work Agencies), 1963 June (Box 6, Folder 57)
        Report on Selected Private Agencies - Their Work and the Negro, by Frankie V. Adams.
      - Assessment Project (Private Social Work Agencies), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 58)
        File contains questionnaire responses for Frankie V. Adams's survey of Private Social Work Agencies and Welfare of the Negro.
      - Assessment Project (Political Parity ), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 59)
        Studies on "Negroes in Policy Making Positions," by Daniel C. Thompson, and on "The Quest for Political Parity," by Henry Lee Moon.
      - Assessment Project (Citizenship and Race Relations), 1963 (Box 6, Folder 60)
        Papers on "The Current Status of Negro-White Relations," by C. Eric Lincoln; and "Citizenship Education," by Robert Moses.
      - Assessment Project (Health), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 61)
        Study on "The Health of the Negro," by Paul B. Cornely, M.D.
      - Assessment Project (Housing), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 62)
        "An Assessment of Housing as a Civil Right," by Corinne R. Morrow, August 1963.
      - Assessment Project (Self-Image of the Negro), 1963 (Box 7, Folder 63)
        Study prepared for the Taconic Foundation by Robert B. Johnson, with Dorothy Height, on "The Self-Image of the Negro," July 1963.
  - Association for Homemaker Service Inc., 1962-1969 (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Association for Homemaker Service Inc., 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Association for Neighborhood and Housing Development
    From 1974-1984, the organization was known as the Association of Neighborhood Housing Developers Inc.
    - 1976-1978 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - 1983 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - 1984 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - 1987 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - 1997-2006 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - (Literature and Reports), 2002 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - (Literature and Reports), 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - (Literature and Reports), 2005 (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Association for Neighborhood and Housing Development (Weatherization Proposal), 1980 (Box 9, Folder 81)